American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIb. 1807-1825 APS.Archives.IIb APS.Archives.IIb
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Letter to Joseph von Hammer[-Purgstall], Vienna, April 25, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.10-12.) Friendly letter on comparative linguistics. Refers to the origin of the American Indian.
  - Letter to [Gottlob Ernst] Schulze, Göttingen, April 27, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.12.) Forwards publications on Indian languages.
  - Extract, April, 1822; Journal des savants
    D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.40.) Concerning Volney and his prize for a new alphabet.
  - Letter to T. Pavenstedt, Bremen, April 29, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.12.) Forwards publications on Indians.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, June 25, 1822; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Lambert, William
    Washington, A.L.S. 3p. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy,vol. 2, no. 104.) Concerning the moon's parallaxes in longitude and latitude.
  - Memorandum, April, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.9.) Concerning a new correspondent, T.Pavenstedt, and instructions as how to ship packages to Heckewelder.
  - Letter to [Johann Severin] Vater, June 16, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.13.) Forwards vocabularies of Indian languages.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, June 29, 1822; 12-1/2x8; Lambert, William
    Washington, A.L.S. 6p.and add. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 105.) Concerning the moon's parallaxes in longitude and latitude.
  - Letter to [Johann Severin] Vater, June 14, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APŠ. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.13.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to P[ierre] A[lexandre] Vernet, June 14, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L. 1p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.13.) Thanks for courtesies. Forwards package to Vater.
  - Letter to Rejoice Newton, Worcester, April 25, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.9.) Von Hammer expresses thanks to the American antiquarian society and will donate publication to it.
  - Analysis of maclurite, May 17, 1822; 7-1/2x8-1/2; Seybert, Henry, 1801-1883
    [read] A.D. 1p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 81.) Cf. Minutes, p.512.
  - Letter to T. Pavenstedt, Bremen, Sept. 27, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.14.) Forwards publication.
  - Description of a new hydrostatic balance, July 1, 1822; 13x8; Coates, Dr.
    [ca.]. D. 4p., table and 2 drawings, end. (see MS Comm. to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng.,etc., nos.48-48b.) Cf. Minutes of Board of officers, July 1, 19, and 20, 1822.
  - Extract, May, 1822; Journal des savants
    D. 3p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol.3, pp.41-43.) Concerning an alphabet to transcribe Asiatic languages into European (the Volney award subject).
  - Letter to [Johann Severin] Vater, July 1, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.14.) Forwards Indian vocabularies.
  - Letter to J[ohann] S. Vater, Sept. 21, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.14.) Thanks for publications. Forwards publications and manuscript on Indian languages.
  - Letter to [Gottlob Ernst] Schulze, Göttingen, Sept. 27, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.15.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to J[ohann] S. Vater, Oct. 20, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.15-17.) Forwards publications. Concerning Indian languages, especially those of Peru.
  - Letter to Isaiah Thomas, Worcester, Nov. 25, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.17-18.) Has received gift of books for the American antiquarian society from various learned societies of Europe.
  - Letter to Abiel Holmes, Nov. 26, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.19.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Sébastien] Bottin, Paris, Nov. 30, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.19-20.) Thanks for publications to the American antiquarian society.
  - Letter to Coquebert de Montbret, Paris, Dec. 1, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 20.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to [Louis André] Pichon, Paris, Dec. 1, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 20.) No resumé made by DuPonceau.
  - Memoir on the non-strangulating hernia and the mode of curing it, Dec. 6, 1822; 11-1/2x8; Elkendorp, B.
    [read] D.S. 16p.and end. In French. (see Ms.Comm. co the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 50.) Cf. Minutes, p.515.
  - Letter to F[riedrich von] Adelung, St. Petersburg, Dec. 22, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.21-23.) Concerning Indian languages.
  - Letter to Joseph von Hammer[-Purgstall,] Vienna, Dec. 22, 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.20-21.) Thanks for donations to the APS and to the American antiquarian society. Forwards publications.
  - List of books requested for the royal library at Göttingen, Dec., 1822; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    [ca.] A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.23-24.)
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Jan. 31, 1823; 10x8; Pedersen, Peder, 1774-1851
    A.L.S. 1p. and end. Forwards publications.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Feb. 20, 1823; 10x8; Ewing, James
    D. 6p.and add.,end. and 2 drawings. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., nos.49,49a.) Concerning a hydrant, entered for the premium. Cf. Minutes, pp.517-518.
  - Letter to Coquebert [de Montbret], March 19, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.24.) Forwards items.
  - Letter to G. W. Featherstonehaugh, Philadelphia, March 23, 1823; 13x8-1/2; Gibson, John Bannister, 1780-1853
    L. Copy. 9p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history vol. 2, no. 63.) Concerning limestone in the Mississippi valley. Cf. Minutes, p.699, 701.
  - Letter to [G.] Barkhausen, April 5, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 24.) Has answered two of his letters.
  - Letter to [T.] Pavenstedt, April 14, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 24.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to [Gottlob Ernst] Schulze, April 15, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
  - Letter to [Isaac Cox] Barnet, April 18, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 25.) Forwards publications.
  - Extract, April, 1823; Journal des savants
    D. 3p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.43-45.) Concerning an alphabet to transcribe Asiatic languages into European (the Volney award subject).
  - Letter to R[obert] Walsh, Philadelphia, May 29, 1823; 10x8; Deabbate, Gaspard
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p.and end. In French. Enc. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 53.) Sends memoir on religious cult of the Vaudois. Cf. Minutes, pp.519-520. For enclosure, see: Deabbate. Concerning...Vaudois: May 29, 1823.
  - Letter to [Gottlob Ernst] Schulze, May 15, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.25.) Forwards publications.
  - Concerning the religious cult of the Vaudois, May 29, 1823; 14x9; Deabbate, Gaspard
    Philadelphia, D. 8p.,end. In French. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 55.) Cf. Minutes, pp.519-520. Enclosed originally in letter from Deabbate to R.Walsh; May 29, 1823.
  - Letter to P[ierre] A[lexandre] Vernet, Hamburg, May 15, 1823; Du Ponceau. Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L. 1p. In French, (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 25.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to [Johann Severin] Vater, June 14, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 26.) Forwarded no publications.
  - J. Man[ue]l Restrepo to Peter S. DuPonceau, May 7, 1823; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Restrepo, José Manuel, 1781-1863
    Bogota, [Columbia], 2 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. (In Spanish.) Forwards Weekly Register of New Granada, II, and a copy of the Constitution of Colombia, to the A. P. S.
  - Extract, June, 1823; Journal des savants
    D.in hand of P.S.DuPonceau. 1p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.26.) Concerning a prize for essay on a new alphabet.
  - Extract of notes concerning a testaceous mass from Anastasia Island, Florida, July 10, 1823; 8x6; Dietz, R.
    [read] D. 6p.,end. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 64.)
  - Letter to R. McCall, Gibralter, Aug. 26, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.26-27.) Asks for books. Thanks for favors.
  - Letter to Jules Klaproth, Paris, Dec. 25, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L. 2p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.28-29.) Forwards publications. Concerning comparative philology.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Sept. 6, 1823; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Fleming, George
    Goochland, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. and 2 drawings. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., nos. 50-50b.) Concerning his method of using steam power.
  - Letter to J[ea]n Sorbé et fils, Nov. 21, 1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.27.) Asks for publication.
  - Meteorological observations made at Washington, April 18, 1823-1824; 12-1/2x8; Wallenstein, Jules de, -1845
    D. 46p.and end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 74.) Cf. Minutes, p.529, 530. For additional information, see letter from Wallenstein to R.Patterson; Aug. 12, 1823.
  - Concerning the air pump, Jan. 21, 1824; 15x8; P., C.
    [read] D.S.with initials. 3p.and add.and drawing of 1p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol.2,no.75.) Cf. Minutes, p.536, 538, 539. Entered for the Magellanic premium(?).
  - Letter to Morandini, Italy, Nov. 29, 1824; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.30-31) Forwards publications. Concerning APS publications.
  - Letter to Coquebert de Montbret, Dec. 15, 1824; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 31.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to Richard Peters, July 2, 1824; 13x8; Waln, Robert, 1794-1825
    Waln Grove, A.L.S. 8p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 56.) Concerning a Chinese book. Cf. Minutes, p.530.
  - Letter to [Johann Severin] Vater, Nov. 31, 1824; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    [sic] Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.31.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to Jos[eph] von Hammer[-Purgstall], Jan. 5, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.32.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to William Shaler, Algiers, Nov. 29, 1824; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.30.) Forwards publications.
  - Memorandum, Jan. 5, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 32.) Delivered publications to Mr. Brunn to be forwarded to Hartmann.
  - Letter to [Joseph von] Hammer-[Purgstall], July, 1824; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.29.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to J[ohn] Vaughan, Oct. 20, 1824; 8x5; Short, William, 1759-1849
    A.L.S. 3p., end., and add., end. Sends medals for A.P.S. collection. Cf. Donation Book, p.38.
  - Concerning the ventilation of ships to prevent the rotting of timbers, Jan. 7, 1825; 12-1/2x8; Barron, James, 1769-1851
    [read] Jan. 7, 1825. D. 5p.and end. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 61.) Entered for the Magellanic premium. Cf. Minutes, pp. 535, 536. For report of committee, see: APS. Report...; Feb. 4, 1825.
  - Letter to [G.] Barkhausen, Bremen, Feb. 17, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks,vol.3.p.32.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to R.M. Patterson, Feb. 3, 1825; 10x8; Long, Stephen Harriman, 1784-1864
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no.60.) Concerning a method of transferring boats of burden. Cf. Minutes, pp.539-540.
  - Letter to [Gottlob Ernst] Schulze, Göttingen, Feb. 17, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 32.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to R.M. Patterson, March 18, 1825; 10x8; Long, Stephen Harriman, 1784-1864
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.and add.,end. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 60a.) Complains of his treatment by the APS. Cf. Minutes, p.540.
  - Letter to Jules Klaproth, April 25, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol.3,p.35.) Forwards publications.
  - Letter to Comte La Forest, April 12, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3,p.34.) Forwards publications. Private letter.
  - Letter to [Isaac Cox] Barnet, April 25, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
  - Letter to Coquebert de Montbret, April 25, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 35.) Forwards money and publications.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Shaler, Algiers, March 31, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp.32-34.) Forwarded his papers to Jared Sparks. Encourages him to write on Africa. Forwards publications.
  - Extract, April, 1825; Journal des savants
    D. 3p. In French. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, pp. 35-37.) Concerning a prize for an essay for a new alphabet.
  - Letter to Jullien [de Paris], Paris, April 25, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 35.) Forwards publications, one of which is for Warden.
  - Letter to Musset Pathay [Victor Donatien de Musset], Paris, May 1, 1825; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 35.) No resumé written by DuPonceau.